A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Projects, Series L FA348
Rockefeller Archive Center
- World Conditions General Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 264, Folder 2642)
  Printed matter discarded. Berent Friele memo on international situation. Roger Kyes would like to discuss world situation with NAR. Various citizens send NAR reports and statements on worlds problems. Correspondents include Benjamin Friedman.
- World Conditions General Correspondence - Clarence A. Lyman, 1952-1958 (Box 264, Folder 2643)
- World Federation of United Nations Associations, 1948-1960 (Box 264, Folder 2644)
  Conrad Wrzos. Recommendations from his friends. Would like to meet with NAR. Recommended to NAR's contacts in Brazil. NAR declines appeals for aid. Correspondents include H. Barrat-Brown.
- World Food Situation, 1947 (Box 264, Folder 2645)
  Milo Perkins memo re "The Food Situation in the Western World," some suggestions for action. NAR appreciation.
- World Statistical Congress, 1947-1949 (Box 264, Folder 2646)
  American National Committee for the International Statistical Conferences, 1947. NAR becomes an Advisory Member. Correspondence re publications and entertaining Latin Americans coming to the Congress.
- World Trade, 1946-1958 (Box 264, Folder 2647)
  Plans to improve world trade. No NAR comments or action.
- World War II, 1946 (Box 264, Folder 2648)
  U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey. Summary Report - Pacific War, 7/1/46. NAR correspondence with Paul Nitze.
- World Welfare and Peace, Inc., 1952-1954 (Box 264, Folder 2649)
  Appeals for financial aid.
- Y Miscellaneous, 1954-1971 (Box 265, Folder 2650)
  General appeals.
- Yablonsky, Dr. Lewis, 1958 (Box 265, Folder 2651)
  Study of juvenile delinquency in New York State. Study and proposal for baseball gangs financed by NAR.
- Yalta Conference, 1951 (Box 265, Folder 2652)
  W. A. Harriman statement in Yalta.
- Yen, Y. C. James, Dr., 1948-1967 (Box 265, Folder 2653)
  China and Philippines, International Institute of Rural Reconstruction. Correspondents include Jimmy Yen and UNESCO.
- Young Men's Christian Association - General, 1949-1971 (Box 265, Folder 2654)
  YMCA Expansion Program, Albany, 1970. YMCA Cleveland Dodge Fund, 1968. YMCA Concord N.H., 1964.
- Young Men's Christian Association - Harlem Branch, 1949-1971 (Box 265, Folder 2655)
  NAR contributions, attended Century Club Dinner, 1949.
- Young Men's Christian Association - Bar Harbor and Mount Desert, etc., 1949-1971 (Box 265, Folder 2656)
  Appeals; declined. Printed matter.
- Young Men's Christian Association - New York City, 1948-1951 (Box 265, Folder 2657)
  Requests for NAR to serve on Board of Directors.
- Young Men's Christian Association - Tarrytown, New York, 1949-1951 (Box 265, Folder 2658)
  General appeals and annual reports for 1948-1951.
- Young Women's Christian Association, 1954-1970 (Box 265, Folder 2659)
  YWCA of the United States of America and National Board. General appeals and donations made. Mrs. Laurance Spelman Rockefeller's involvement in Fund Raising Committee. Clippings. Memo to Mrs. Laurance Spelman Rockefeller.
- Young Women's Christian Association - White Plains, N.Y., 1965-1970 (Box 265, Folder 2660)
  General appeals for financial aid.
- Youth Builders, 1949 (Box 265, Folder 2661)
  NAR declines appeal. Correspondents include Newbold Morris.
- Z Miscellaneous, 1960-1971 (Box 266, Folder 2662)
- Zeckendorf, William and Son, 1949-1965 (Box 266, Folder 2663)
  Miscellaneous clippings and correspondence with NAR.
- Ziffern, Lester, 1948 (Box 266, Folder 2664)
  Coordinator's office press man in Chile. Received Civilian Award. Correspondents include Francis A. Jamieson.
- Zingaro, Anthony, 1962-1963 (Box 266, Folder 2665)
  Engineer. Wanted to buy Rockwood Hall to build 300 houses.
- Zorach, William, Sculptor, 1956-1966 (Box 266, Folder 2666)
  Correspondence re NAR and Zorach's artwork. Correspondence with Edith Halpert and Oveta Culp Hobby. Dallas controversy. Died in 1966.
- Zuccala, George S. Dr., 1958-1960 (Box 266, Folder 2667)
  Seeks support for his cancer cures. Polite staff declinations.
- United States Government
  - General, 1948-1969 (Box 266, Folder 2668)
    Memos on current affairs. Correspondence re: Congressional activities, appointments, special committees, and reports. Clippings.
  - Agency for International Development (AID), 1968 (Box 266, Folder 2669)
  - Department of Agriculture, 1956-1958 (Box 266, Folder 2670)
    NAR declines to serve on Distinguished Awards Committee. Supermarkets in Venezuela. Correspondents include Raymond Ogg.
  - U.S. Arts Foundation and Harrison Committee, 1954-1957 (Box 266, Folder 2671)
    Federal Fine Arts Program, also called U.S. Art Commission. "Guidelines for a National Program in the Arts." NAR a member of Government in Art Committee. Support for bills HR 5756 and S1716. Congressional record. Correspondents include Frank Thompson, Jr., Rene d'Harnoncourt.
  - Art Bill and Medal for Distinguished Civilian Achievement, 1954-1964 (Box 267, Folder 2672)
    NAR support for bill to provide for establishment of a Federal Advisory Commission on the Arts. Various letters and memos in connection with the bill. Correspondents Lloyd Goodrich.
  - Art Bill and Medal for Distinguished Civilian Achievement - Text of bills, hearings, memos, 1954-1964 (Box 267, Folder 2673)
  - Atomic Energy Commission (AEC), 1952-1960 (Box 267, Folder 2674)
    Reports to NAR on progress and investigations of the Commission.
  - Bureau of the Budget, 1952-1954 (Box 267, Folder 2675)
    Printed matter discarded. NAR praise for Hughes' address on the 1954 Federal Budget. Clipping on Eisenhower budget.
  - Civil Defense, 1957-1958 (Box 267, Folder 2676)
    HR 2125 Bill; NAR interest but declines to present his ideas on shelters to Congress. Suggests others from Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies.
  - Civil Rights, 1957 (Box 267, Folder 2677)
    Francis A. Jamieson summary of progress of Civil Rights Bill.
  - Civil Service Commission, 1957-1962 (Box 267, Folder 2678)
    Correspondence re: positions in Civil Service. Clippings. Civil Service 75th anniversary celebration, 1958. Recommendation for Mrs. Williams for civil service job in 1962.
  - Department of Commerce, 1949-1955 (Box 267, Folder 2679)
    NAR sees Bern Gladieux. "Ways to increase U.S. imports of Strategic Materials from Latin America." Business Advisory Council Dinner attended.
  - Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government, Hoover Commission, 1949-1952 (Box 267, Folder 2680)
    John F. Meck interview with NAR. Chart on executive branch of government. Senate action on Hoover Commission reports.
  - Committee on Government Operations, Organization of Federal Executive Departments and Agencies, 1949-1961 (Box 268, Folder 2681)
    Charts, printed material. Memos on organization of committees and government operations.
  - Defense Department, 1949-1966 (Box 268, Folder 2682)
    Printed material. Clippings, material on Defense Production Act of 1950. Correspondence re appointments and reports on Defense Department activities. Correspondence with Charles E. Wilson. Material on Vietnam.
  - Defense, Office of the Secretary of: Joint Orientation Conference, 1948-1949 (Box 268, Folder 2683)
    Joint Orientation Conference, 1948. Attended by NAR. James Forrestal's appreciation for NAR's advice. Correspondents include John E. Lockwood.
  - Defense, Office of the Secretary of: Joint Orientation Conference - Memos and Drafts, 1949 (Box 268, Folder 2684)
    Preparation of letter to James Forrestal.
  - Defense Department Reorganization, 1958 (Box 268, Folder 2685)
    Neil McElroy's Committee. NAR served as consultant. John McCone remarks on defense organization, congratulations to NAR as consultant to Secretary of Defense. NAR meetings in Washington. President's message on defense reorganization. Reactions of other businessmen. Correspondents include Al Gruenther, Irving Guest, Arthur Sommerfield.
  - Defense Department Reorganization: Clippings, 1953, 1958 (Box 268, Folder 2686)
  - Defense Orientation Conference Association, 1950-1967 (Box 269, Folder 2687)
    NAR a member of association and a participant in Joint Civilian Orientation Conferences, 1951-1952. Invitations to join and to participate in meetings. Correspondence with Commander J. P. Floyd re the conference. Printed material, by-laws. Form letters discarded.
  - Defense Orientation Conference Association: Printed Material, 1951-1971 (Box 269, Folder 2688)
  - NOT USED (Box 269, Folder 2689)
  - NOT USED (Box 269, Folder 2690)
  - Department of Defense: "Commander's Digest", 1966-1967 (Box 269, Folder 2691)
    Vol. II, no. 5 - Vol. III, No. 29 of newsletter on defense activities.
  - Eisenhower Cabinet Staff Appointees, 1952-1954 (Box 269, Folder 2692)
    NAR letters of congratulations to appointees, their gratitude.
  - NOT USED (Box 269, Folder 2693)
  - Employees, 1950-1956 (Box 269, Folder 2694)
    Various recommendations by NAR and personal notes recommending others to NAR. Correspondents include Murray Snyder, Vance Rogers, Frank Lindsay, Clyde Brothers, Albert Gieseche.
  - Export Import Bank of Washington, 1947-1957 (Box 269, Folder 2695)
    Annual reports sent to NAR. Memo on meeting at the bank. Personal Correspondence. Correspondents include Bill Martin, Jr., Shaw Cole.
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1940-1949 (Box 269, Folder 2696)
    Analyses for NAR of Paul Henry Nitze for recommendations to Advisory Commission to the Council of National Defense. NAR's praise of FBI and J. Edgar Hoover.
  - Federal Fundraising, 1956 (Box 269, Folder 2697)
    NAR contributes to Federal Service Campaign for National Health Agencies and Federal Service Joint Crusade. NAR drops out of campaign.
  - Foreign Policy and Foreign Economic Policy, 1953-1956 (Box 269, Folder 2698)
    Personal notes. Printed material sent to NAR. Harlan Cleveland statement and Stacy May reaction. Clippings on Dulles and foreign policy. NAR declines to meet with Committee on Foreign Affairs.
  - Foreign Trade Agreements, 1947-1949 (Box 269, Folder 2699)
    NAR praise for Eric Johnston statement on foreign trade before Ways and Means Committee. Declines to meet with R. J. Clark.
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1956-1960 (Box 270, Folder 2700)
    Printed matter. Rehabilitation advice from Bernard Baruch. NAR recommends Victor d'Amico to check Children's Art Exhibit. NAR congratulates Sam Brownwell. "The Negro Family's Search for Economic Security." Personal letters. General Affairs Foundation. NAR support for HR 6771. Dr. Barbara Moulton statement. Correspondents include Mary Taylor, Marion Folsom.
  - U. S. Information Agency (USIA): General, 1956-1965 (Box 270, Folder 2701)
    Clippings, memos, correspondence re USIA activities. Correspondents include William Jackson, Arthur Larsen, Tracy Voorhees, Ted Streibert, William Clark, George Allen.
  - U.S. Information Agency (USIA): Radio Symposium - Frontiers of Knowledge, Moving Science Toward the Equator, 1957 (Box 270, Folder 2702)
    NAR's participation, taping of the address.
  - U.S. Information Agency (USIA): U.S. Information Service (USIS), 1956-1958 (Box 270, Folder 2703)
    Correspondence re: USIS activities.
  - U.S. Information Agency (USIA): Barometer Survey, Public Opinion Reports, 1957 (Box 270, Folder 2704)
    Reports on opinion trends. Correspondence re surveys.
  - Legislation, 1949-1956 (Box 270, Folder 2705)
    The Flanders Bill: NAR indicates that it does not need his support. Various letters to NAR re proposed legislation. Printed matter. Correspondents include Bill Benton, Francis P. Bolton.
  - Maritime Commission: Kings Point Academy, 1948 (Box 270, Folder 2706)
    NAR declines visit to Kings Point Academy. Personal note. Correspondents include Dick Parkhurst.
  - Maritime Commission, 1947-1948 (Box 270, Folder 2707)
    NAR investigates Material Scientifico C.A. for Richard Parkhurst, Commissioner. NAR regrets Parkhurst will leave Maritime Commission.
  - Mutual Security Act and Agency, 1951-1956 (Box 271, Folder 2708)
    Correspondence re: foreign aid bill. NAR statement before committee on Foreign Affairs. Correspondents include Edward G. Miller, Jr., Christian Herter, Frank Barnett.
  - ECA Administration (formerly Marshall Plan), 1947-1951 (Box 271, Folder 2709)
    NAR declines to serve on U.S. Associates Committee on Europe. Printed material and addresses sent to NAR. Digest of pertinent articles sent to NAR. Peace plan suggestions sent to Rockefeller Brothers by E. McCloskey and other civilians. Correspondents include Milo Perkins, Philip Reed, Stacy May, Wayne Taylor.
  - Peace Corps, 1961 (Box 271, Folder 2710)
    Correspondence with Chester Bowles. A letter concerning an applicant.
  - Point IV
    - General Correspondence, Civilian Interests, 1950-1957 (Box 271, Folder 2711)
      Various miscellaneous correspondence and reports from civilians interested in the foreign aid program.
    - Brazil, 1951 (Box 271, Folder 2712)
    - Information Service, 1951-1952 (Box 271, Folder 2713)
      Correspondence re: Dewey Anderson (chairman). NAR contributed in 1951. Clippings, articles.
    - Clippings, 1952 (Box 271, Folder 2714)
      Clippings from U.S. newspapers, material from U.S. Information Service.
    - U.S. Council of the International Chamber of Commerce, 1949 (Box 271, Folder 2715)
      Printed matter. Thanks to NAR for helpfulness at Panel Session on American Business and Point IV. Correspondents include Alvin E. Dodd.
    - Legislation, 1949 (Box 271, Folder 2716)
      HR 5615 and NAR testimony. Printed matter. HR 6026. Correspondents include Philip Watts.
    - Clippings, 1949-1950 (Box 271, Folder 2717)
    - Export Import Bank Act, 1949 (Box 271, Folder 2718)
    - NAR's Testimony, 1949 (Box 271, Folder 2719)
    - NAR Material, 1949 (Box 272, Folder 2720)
      Suggestion revision in testimony. Manuscript from Foreign Affairs Committee.
    - National Conference on International Economic and Social Development, 1952 (Box 272, Folder 2721)
      General Correspondence. NAR a sponsor.
    - National Conference on International Economic and Social Development: Printed matter, 1952 (Box 272, Folder 2722)
    - Post-War Council, James P. Warburg, 1950 (Box 272, Folder 2723)
      Pamphlets and clippings. NAR declines meeting sponsored by Council. Correspondents include Mary Hillyer.
    - General, 1949-1952 (Box 272, Folder 2724)
      Various memos and statements regarding Point IV. NAR praises Sawyer's speech, "American and World Trade." Digests of articles. Norman Littrell address. Correspondents include Brooks Emery.
    - General: National Foreign Trade Council, 1949-1950 (Box 272, Folder 2725)
    - General: John E. Lockwood - Policy Statement, 1949 (Box 272, Folder 2726)
    - General - Christian A. Herter, 1949 (Box 272, Folder 2727)
    - General - American Association for the U.N., Inc., 1949 (Box 272, Folder 2728)
    - Printed Matter, 1952 (Box 273, Folder 2729)
      "Opportunities for All." "The Reformation of the World's Economy." "Point IV."
  - Post Office Department, 1953 (Box 273, Folder 2730)
    NAR interest in Latin American postal rates.
  - President's Council on Youth Fitness, 1957 (Box 273, Folder 2731)
    Printed matter and Steven David memorandum on the Council. Correspondents include Shane McCarthy.
  - Public Administration, 1953 (Box 273, Folder 2732)
    Possible publications by Bureau of the Budget.
  - NAR Statement on Senate Investigating Committee on National Preparedness, 1958 (Box 273, Folder 2733)
    Text. Statement made as a result of Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project paper, "International Security: The Military Aspect."
  - Reciprocal Trade Agreements, 1958 (Box 273, Folder 2734)
    Printed matter. HR 1211. Frank Thompson's suggestions re Reciprocal Trade Bill.
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1950-1956 (Box 273, Folder 2735)
    Would like NAR to testify on bipartisan Senate resolution. Declined due to absence from country. NAR praise for Mike Mansfield. Comments re developments in India: S. Res. 243. Correspondents include Bill Benton.
  - Social Security, 1953 (Box 273, Folder 2736)
    Victor Borella study; "U.S. Social Security Program Today." Rosalind G. Baldwin memos and work sheets on the "State Option" plan of each state.
  - Department of State: General Correspondence, 1945-1971 (Box 273, Folder 2737)
    Correspondence between NAR and Carl McCardle re McCardle's resignation from the Dept. of State, 1957. Summary of Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs Henry Holland's speech, "U.S. Economic Relations with South America," 1954. Correspondence re: special activities, meetings, appointments. "Employee Loyalty Investigation." Reports on proposals, policies, and Latin American affairs. Clippings, printed material.
  - Department of State: Passport Office, 1949-1970 (Box 273, Folder 2738)
    Correspondence re passports for NAR and others. Passport office in Rockefeller Center.
  - Department of State: Division of Historical Research, 1947-1948 (Box 273, Folder 2739)
    Correspondence re interview on War History of the State Department with Mr. Gosnell.
  - Department of State: Committee on Inter-American Affairs, n.d. (Box 274, Folder 2740)
    Berent Friele will serve on committee for NAR.
  - Department of State: International Cooperation Administration, 1958 (Box 274, Folder 2741)
    Robert W. Purcell will meet with Japanese executives for NAR. Printed material.
  - Department of State: International Development Advisory Board (IDAB), 1952 (Box 274, Folder 2742)
    NAR chairman. Stacy May memo on visit of the IDAB. NAR comments on IDAB policy statement. Requests for IDAB report, "Partners in Progress." Correspondents include Harvey Firestone, Eric Johnston, John C. Cady.
  - Department of State: U.S. International Information Administration, 1953 (Box 274, Folder 2743)
    NAR praises Robert Johnston's work. "Report on the Book and Library program."
  - Department of State: International Information and Cultural Affairs Office, 1948 (Box 274, Folder 2744)
    Press release re organization of office. OIC budget estimate as submitted to Congress.
  - Department of State: Technical Cooperation Administration, 1952 (Box 274, Folder 2745)
    Requests for "Partners in Progress." NAR congratulates Stanley Andrews on becoming administrator of TCA.
  - Department of State: Voice of America (VOA), 1951-1954 (Box 274, Folder 2746)
    Printed matter discarded. NAR declined to make broadcast for Pan American Day. Correspondents include James S. Carson.
  - Technical Men, Education of, 1957 (Box 274, Folder 2747)
    Memo to NAR re G.I. assistance and education of technical men. Correspondents include Jim Killian, Gail Moulton.
  - Treasury Department, 1947-1957 (Box 274, Folder 2748)
    Vernon Clark asks NAR's advice re recruiting of volunteer personnel to increase sales of U.S. savings bonds. NAR suggestions.
  - Treasury Department: Bureau of Internal Revenue, 1947 (Box 274, Folder 2749)
  - Truman, President Harry S., 1945-1951 (Box 274, Folder 2750)
    Would like NAR to see F. G. Pendergast. NAR member of General Committee in charge of the 1949 inaugural. Harry S. Truman praises NAR. Personal notes.
  - War Assets Administration, 1946-1947 (Box 274, Folder 2751)
    NAR will help Robert Field launch program in Brazil. Record of the War Assets Administration showing monthly deposits. Correspondents include Stacy May.
  - War Department, 1947 (Box 274, Folder 2752)
    NAR declines meeting on War Department security needs. Clipping. Correspondents include Howard Peterson.
- Rockefeller Center, Inc. - Rainbow Room - Scrapbook, 1935-1939 (Box 275, Folder 2753)
  Magazine articles, newspaper clippings, advertisements, and programs on entertainment at the Rainbow Room, as well as menus, assembled by John Roy, Managing Director of Center Restaurants, Inc. It includes two pieces of NAR correspondence and a few pieces of correspondence from entertainers. Presumably, Mr. Roy reused a binder he already had to assemble this scrapbook, thus the cover refers to the Young Women's League of the Home of the Daughters of Israel, even though none of the content relates to that group.